Trend structure can be broken down into
two main phases swing structure and
substructure and if you can understand
how to differentiate swing structure
from substructure you can take some
brilliant trades and have a better
understanding of the marker overall so
what's the difference between swing
structure and substructure and how can
we use it to our advantage what you can
see here on the screen is a standard
trending move and what we get within a
trending move are higher highs and
higher lows this of course is a standard
uptrend because we can see the market
continuing to climb higher forming those
higher highs and higher lows of course
if we were in a downtrend it would
actually be printing lower highs and
lower lows and would be moving the other
way now this is the structure that I
like to call the swing structure now
swing structure can refer to any time
frame so let's say you were looking at
the hourly time frame in this example
this is what we would see we would see
an hourly uptrend or hourly bullish
swing structure however within the
larger swing uptrend we will actually
see smaller substructure downtrends
happening on these corrective moves for
reference Trends are made up of two main
phases we have impulses and Corrections
an Impulse is a move in line with the
direction of the trend so in an uptrend
the upward move will be the impulse and
the pullback move which is the little
pull down lower we get before the next
impulse is called a correction because
the market is correcting itself
So within this hourly uptrend what we
will see if we zoom in is a collection
of lower time frame uptrends and
downtrends within this price action and
that would look something a little like
this so we have the overall swing
uptrend and within that we'll see a
progression of smaller waves to the
upside and within the corrective move we
will actually have an entire Trend to
the downside So within every uptrend we
will actually see lower time frame
downtrends when we start to scale
through the time frames and this is what
we call sub structure so the way that we
can use substructure to our advantage is
to actually trade through these smaller
Trends within the larger trends that
price has formed
so for example if we were looking at
this trend from a buy perspective we
would be looking to buy on the pullbacks
however what if we got confirmation such
as here to actually sell the corrective
move using valid structure so that we
weren't really trading counter Trend but
we were trading Pro Trend with a lower
time frame
let's head over to the charts and I'll
show you an example of this in action
okay guys so for our example we're
looking at GBP USD and here we can see
on the four hour time frame that the
swing structure is bullish okay because
we have an Impulse with a break of
structure over the previous highs then
we have a correction and then we have an
Impulse okay so we have our swing
structure intact and we can see that
that is pointing to the upside now what
we can do is break down imbalances and
supply and demand zones to see where the
prime place to buy from would be and by
doing that I can pretty much see that
this area here is the prime high
probability buy point for GBP USD if we
pull back into this point now if we look
previous we can see we had a demand Zone
here which was retested before the trend
continued up so I would say the
likelihood of price coming back down
here is quite slim however the
likelihood of price pulling to this area
is quite high so what we would look for
is a pullback to this level where we can
then buy and take make the market higher
so that's the swing structure covered
and that leads us onto the substructure
where do the substructor trend
opportunities come in well we can see
that previously we had this corrective
move just here and within this
corrective move we actually saw the
market break structure at this point
into a lower low pull back and form a
lower high and then continue forming
lower lows and lower highs until the
market reversed so you can see there
that on a low end of time frame basis
the market did actually turn into a
downtrend just to come and fill back
into some of the Swing structure now
what we can see in the current example
is that we once again had a break of
structure here so this may indicate to
us that this is the beginning of a new
substructure move and what we would look
for is a substructure pull down towards
that demand Zone that we marked out for
high probability bytes so what we can do
now is actually look for the selling
opportunities in the new downtrend
formed by this substructure break of
structure and see if we can find an
opportunity to trade down towards that
high probability buying point at the
bottom of this swing structure move
something I wanted to share with you
very quickly I'm now trading live with
my team every day so if you want to get
access to my fundamental and technical
analysis by the week get all of my trade
updates prior to me entering and try it
live with me every day in a network of
over 1 000 enthusiastic students as a
subscription open for that now I'll see
you on the inside so for this let's go
to the 15 minute time frame and assess
the structure from this point okay so
now that we're on the lower time frame
we can actually very clearly see this
shift in the trend we had this higher
high higher low higher high and as we
can see this higher low has actually now
broken into a series of lower lows so
what we would do is look for a high
probability area to sell from and then
we can place our sell orders and see if
we can write this down as far through
this Wing structure move as possible
inside of this new substructure
downtrend now at a glance I can see that
this area here is quite high probability
because we haven't actually retested
this level just yet as you can see by
the little Gap in the Wicks there so
what I would go ahead and do at this
point is place our sell order on this
point here put a stop loss over the high
and then we could actually use this
trade to Target down into that area we
were looking at from a substructure
perspective and now even if this entry
doesn't hit we can simply follow the
market down from the point of view of a
15 minute downtrend because that is what
we're now in until we reach some of
these high probability areas now of
course because we are counter Trend to
the larger four-hour Trend which is
going to be the more accurate Trend we
should always make sure we are looking
at possible reversal points for example
demand zones like this one and maybe
even this one as well and in a real
scenario we would be considering taking
some profit at these levels or at least
trailing our stop losses and going break
even so that we can maximize our profits
regardless of whether the move gets all
the way through to the Target or not so
for the sake of keeping it neat I've
gone up to the hourly time frame here
and I'm going to monitor whether this is
tapped in and whether the trade then
fills out to Target
let's take a look
[Music]
foreign
did fill our entry and then consistently
traded down through that 15 minute
downtrend to fill the target as you can
see there were also additional Supply
zones that we could have sold into the
market so now that we've reached this
substructure level what would be our
next move well our next move would be
focused back on the buy side along with
that four hour Trend so what we could do
at this point is buy into the market
with our stop loss below and we could
Target the highs looking to continue the
swing Trend once again so let's see how
that goes
[Music]
and there we have it you can see a
successful substructure Trend and a
swing structure trending trade using the
lower time frame and the higher time
frame structure and that is how you can
differentiate substructure and swing
structure and profit from Trading both
this method should allow you to catch
more high probability trades and also
give you a better understanding of which
Trend you should be following right now
I hope that you found this video
beneficial if you have please drop a
like and make sure you subscribe because
I post educational videos here every
week thank you for watching make sure
you don't forget to check out the free
course and I'll see you in the next
video
foreign